Guide to the Office of the Comptroller records, 1874-2002 RG0064
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Office of the Comptroller records
1874-2002
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
George Washington University. Office of the Comptroller
RG0064
40 Linear Feet
Collection includes quarterly appraisals of the university's securities, trust fund ledgers and journals, grants and contracts,schedules of financial statements and annual financial reports.
Restrictions on Access
Series 2, 4, and 5 are closed to research for 50 years from date of record creation.
Access to student records is governed by the federal Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA), which protects the privacy of student education records. Student records in Series 6 are closed for 100 years from date of record creation.
Acquisition Information
Materials acquired through transfers from the Office of the Comptroller.
Historical or Biographical Note
The Comptroller's Office is responsible for management of the University's administrative financial operations which include the accounting, payroll, student accounts, grants and contracts, and administrative financial systems.
Collection Scope and Content
Materials in the collection include quarterly appraisals of the university's securities, trust fund ledgers and journals, policies and procedures, general ledger funds, grants and contracts, application, loan, registrar forms, commencement materials, schedules of financial statements and annual financial reports (including departmental funds, building funds by name, square and lot number, endowment funds and sponsored research). The collection covers the years 1874 to 2002. Note: Not all series are processed. Ask staff for assistance.
Collection Organization
Organized into eight series: Financial statements and annual financial reports; Trust fund ledgers and journals; Handbooks and records; Policies and procedures, general ledger funds; Grants and contracts; Application, loan, registrar forms, commencement materials; Quarterly appraisal of the university's securities; and University budget.
Endowments; Washington (D.C.); Contracts; Research grants; Financial statements; Budget; George Washington University
- Financial statements and annual financial reports, 1874-2002; RG0064 Series 1; 8 Linear feet (Box 9, Box 3, Box 8, Box 4, Box 5, Box 6, Box 7, Box 1, Box 2)
  Scope and Contents note
  This series includes schedules of financial statements and annual financial reports (including departmental funds; building funds by name, square and lot number; endowment funds, and sponsored research). They date from 1874-2002.
  Formerly ACC#44.
  - Report of the Treasurer - The George Washington University, 1876-1892 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Report of the Treasurer - The George Washington University, 1893-1902 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Report of the Treasurer - The George Washington University, 1903-1912 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Report of the Treasurer - The George Washington University, 1913-1919 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Report of the Treasurer - The George Washington University, 1920-1926 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Report of the Treasurer - The George Washington University, 1927-1935 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Report of the Treasurer - The George Washington University, 1936-1942 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Report of the Treasurer - The George Washington University, 1943-1947 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Report of the Comptroller, 1944, 1952; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Report of the Treasurer - The George Washington University, 1948-1952 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Report of the Treasurer - The George Washington University, 1953-1956 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Report of the Treasurer - The George Washington University, 1953-1960; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Report of the Treasurer - The George Washington University, 1957-1960 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Report of the Treasurer - The George Washington University, 1961-1964 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Report of the Treasurer - The George Washington University, 1961-1966; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Report of the Treasurer - The George Washington University, 1965-1968 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Report of the Treasurer - The George Washington University, 1968-1971; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Report of the Treasurer - The George Washington University, 1969-1971 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Annual Report - The George Washington University, 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Annual Report - The George Washington University, 1972-1978; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Annual Report - The George Washington University, 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Annual Report - The George Washington University, 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Annual Report - The George Washington University, 1979-1984; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - The George Washington University Annual Report, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - The George Washington University Annual Report, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - The George Washington University Annual Report, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - The George Washington University Annual Report, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - The George Washington University Annual Report, 1984-1986 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - The George Washington University Annual Report, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Annual Report - The George Washington University, 1985-1989; Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - The George Washington University Annual Report, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - The George Washington University Annual Report, 1987-1989 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - The George Washington University Schedules to the Finacial Statements For the year ended June 30, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    General note
    2 Copies
  - The George Washington University Financial Report, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - The George Washington University Financial Report, 1990-1991 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - The George Washington University Schedules to the Finacial Statements For the year ended June 30, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - The George Washington University Schedules to the Finacial Statements For the year ended June 30, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    2 Copies; also Includes 1991-1992 Finacial Report
  - The George Washington University Schedules to the Finacial Statements For the year ended June 30, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    2 Copies; also Includes 1992-1993 Financial Report
  - The George Washington University Schedules to the Finacial Statements For the year ended June 30, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    Also includes 1993-1994 Finacial Report
  - The George Washington University Schedules to the Finacial Statements For the year ended June 30, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - The George Washington University Schedules to the Finacial Statements For the year ended June 30, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    2 copies; also includes University Financial Reports 1994-1995
  - The George Washington University Schedules to the Finacial Statements For the year ended June 30, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    Also includes Financial Reports 1995-1996
  - Financial Report, 1996-1997 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Financial Report, 1997-1998 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Financial Report, 1998-1999 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - The George Washington University Schedules to the Financial Statements For the year ended June 30, 1999 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    Volume 1 of 2
  - The George Washington University Schedules to the Financial Statements For the year ended June 30, 1999 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    Volume 2 of 2
  - Financial Report, 1999-2000 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - The George Washington University Schedules to the Financial Statement For the year ended June 30, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - The George Washington University Schedules to the Financial Statement For the year ended June 30, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Financial Report, 2000-2002 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - The George Washington University Schedules to the Financial Statements For the Year Ended June 30, 1981 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - The George Washington University Schedules to the Financial Statements For the Year Ended June 30, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - The George Washington University Schedules to the Financial Statements For the Year Ended June 30, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - The George Washington University Schedules to the Financial Statements For the Year Ended June 30, 1984 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - The George Washington University Schedules to the Financial Statements For the Year Ended June 30, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Financial report, 1990-1995; Series 1 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - The George Washington University Schedules to the Financial Statements For the Year Ended June 30, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - The George Washington University Schedules to the Financial Statements For the Year Ended June 30, 1995 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Financial report, 1995-1999; Series 1 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - The George Washington University Schedules to the Financial Statements For the Year Ended June 30, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - The George Washington University Schedules to the Financial Statements For the Year Ended June 30, 1997 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - The George Washington University Schedules to the Financial Statements For the Year Ended June 30, 1998 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - The George Washington University Schedules to the Financial Statements For the Year Ended June 30, 1999 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - The George Washington University Schedules to the Financial Statements For the Year Ended June 30, 1999 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Financial report, 1999-2003; Series 1 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - The George Washington University Schedules to the Financial Statements For the Year Ended June 30, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - The George Washington University Schedules to the Financial Statements For the Year Ended June 30, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - The George Washington University Schedules to the Financial Statements For the Year Ended June 30, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - The George Washington University Schedules to the Financial Statements For the Year Ended June 30, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - The George Washington University Schedules to the Financial Statements For the Year Ended June 30, 2002 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - The George Washington University Schedules to the Financial Statements For the Year Ended June 30, 2002 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Financial report, 2003-2006; Series 1 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Financial report, 2006-2009; Series 1 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - The George Washington University Reports of the Treasurer, 1876-1892 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - The George Washington University Reports of the Treasurer, 1893-1902 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - The George Washington University Reports of the Treasurer, 1903-1912 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - The George Washington University Reports of the Treasurer, 1913-1919 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - The George Washington University Reports of the Treasurer, 1920-1926 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - The George Washington University Reports of the Treasurer, 1936-1942 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - The George Washington University Reports of the Treasurer for the months ended June 30, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - The George Washington University Schedules Reports of the Treasurer for the months ended June 30, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    Also includes 1967 Financial Report of the Treasurer
  - The George Washington University Schedules Reports of the Treasurer for the months ended June 30, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    Also includes 1968 Financial Report of the Treasurer
  - The George Washington University Schedules Report of the Treasurer for the months ended June 30, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    Also includes 1969 Financial Report of the Treasurer
  - The George Washington University Schedules Report of the Treasurer for the months ended June 30, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - The George Washington University Schedules Report of the Treasurer for the months ended June 30, 1971 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    Also includes 1971 Financial Report of the Treasurer
  - The George Washington University Schedules Report of the Treasurer for the months ended June 30, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - The George Washington University Schedules Report of the Treasurer for the months ended June 30, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - The George Washington University Schedules Report of the Treasurer for the months ended June 30, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - The George Washington University Schedules Report of the Treasurer for the months ended June 30, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - The George Washington University Schedules Report of the Treasurer for the months ended June 30, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - The George Washington University Schedules Report of the Treasurer for the months ended June 30, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - The George Washington University Schedules Report of the Treasurer for the months ended June 30, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Recommendations for Improvement in Internal Accounting Controls and Procedures, April - October, 1973; These reports were prepared for and submitted to the GW University Office of the Comptroller by Price Waterhouse and Co. Includes two seperate reports submitted in April and October, 1973, respectively. Originally filed under Acc. #855. Documents have been rehoused from there original binder. (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Price Waterhouse and Co. Audits, 1973; Various files related to audits performed by Price Waterhouse and Co. on behalf of The George Washington Unviersity during the fiscal year of 1973. Includes various proposals and recommendations regarding the university's handlings of various government aid programs. Files rehoused from a binder originally titled "Management Letters" and cataloged under Acc. #855, #16. (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Letter Regarding 1974 Financial Statements, Contains letter to Comptroller Frederick J. Narramore regarding financial statements for the 1973-74 fiscal year. Letter was rehoused from a binder originally titled "Management Letters." Originally catalogued under Acc. #855, #16. (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - 1975 Fiscal Year Letters, 1975-76; Series of letters regarding audits and reports created by Price Waterhouse and Co. prepared for The George Washington University. Most particularly address recommendations made for George Washington University's Medical Center. Files were rehoused from a binder originally titled "Management Letters" and cataloged under Acc.#855, #16. (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Recommendations for Improvement in Internal Accounting Controls and Procedures, November, 1977; These reports were prepared for and submitted to the GW University Office of the Comptroller by Price Waterhouse and Co. Includes two seperate reports submitted on November 1, 1977. Rehoused from original binder, titled "Management Letters" and cataloged under Acc. #855, #16. (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Recommendations for Improvement in Internal Accounting Controls and Procedures, October, 1978; These reports were prepared for and submitted to the GW University Office of the Comptroller by Price Waterhouse and Co. Includes two seperate reports submitted on October 20, 1978. Rehoused from original binder, titled "Management Letters" and cataloged under Acc. #855, #16. (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Recommendations for Improvement in Internal Accounting Controls and Procedures, August, 1979; These reports were prepared for and submitted to the GW University Office of the Comptroller by Price Waterhouse and Co. Includes two seperate reports submitted on August 2, 1979. Rehoused from original binder, titled "Management Letters" and cataloged under Acc. #855, #16. (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Recommendations for Improvement in Internal Accounting Controls and Administrative Efficiency, September, 1980; These reports were prepared for and submitted to the GW University Office of the Comptroller by Price Waterhouse and Co. Includes two seperate reports submitted on September 2, 1980. Rehoused from original binder, titled "Management Letters" and cataloged under Acc. #855, #16. (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Recommendations for Improvement in Internal Accounting Controls and Administrative Efficiency, September, 1981; These reports were prepared for and submitted to the GW University Office of the Comptroller by Price Waterhouse and Co. Includes two seperate reports submitted on September 11, 1981. Rehoused from original binder, titled "Management Letters" and cataloged under Acc. #855, #16. (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Recommendations for Improvement in Internal Accounting Controls and Administrative Efficiency, September, 1982; These reports were prepared for and submitted to the GW University Office of the Comptroller by Price Waterhouse and Co. Includes two seperate reports submitted on September 13, 1982. Rehoused from original binder, titled "Management Letters" and cataloged under Acc. #855, #16. (Box 10, Folder 10)
- Trust fund ledgers and journals, ca. 1920-1986; RG0064 Series 2; 13.5 Linear feet
  This series contains trust fund ledgers and journals from ca. 1920-86. Ledgers and journals prior to 1950 are not restricted.
  - Trust Funds: General Journal, 07/01/1967-12/16/1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Trust Funds: Assets, 1980 ca. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Trust Funds: Assets, 1970 ca. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Endowment And Loan Funds Ledger, 1960-1980 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Trust Funds General Journal, 11/27/1979-09/24/1981 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Trust Funds General Journal, 09/24/1981-05/31/1983 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Trust Funds General Journal, 06/02/1983-06/30/1985 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Trust Funds General Journal, 12/16/1976-11/27/1979 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Trust Funds Receipts, 07/05/1979-04/23/1986 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Trust Funds Disbursements, 11/13/1975-09/29/1981 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Trust Funds Disbursements, 10/07/1981-06/24/1986 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Trust Funds Vouchers, 1961-62, November, 1961 - August, 1961; Trust Fund Vouchers and Cashed Checks from GWU Trust Fund Accounts over 10 months of time. Vouchers are yellow and in individual bundles by month. Cashed checks are green and bundled in order by month. All checks and vouchers are in a reddish-brown records box. (Carton 1, Folder 1)
  - Trust Funds Vouchers, 1970, January, 1970 - September, 1970; Trust Fund Vouchers and Cashed Checks from GWU Trust Fund Accounts over 10 months of time. Vouchers are yellow and in individual bundles by month. Cashed checks are green and bundled in order by month. All checks and vouchers are in a reddish-brown records box. (Carton 1, Folder 2)
  - General University Ledger (Salaries, Appropriations, etc), 1939 - 1940; Ledger of the University's expenses including categories on: capital, administration, general funds, other funds, refund, junior college, botany, english, graduate programs, expendatures, research, law, education, government, summer programs, physical education, library, maintainance, services and rentals, hospital, opthalmology, duplicates and storage, athletics, and student accounts. Originally accessioned in June, 2000 and categorized under Acc. 855 #37.; Fair condition, handle with care. Velvet cover with cracking red leather binding. Bolt bound. Measures 14" x 12" x 4.5". (Carton 2)
  - General Ledger - Closed Accounts, 1948 - c. 1968; Contains information about closed accounts across various departments of the University. Ledger is based on accounts which were closed between 1948-1968. Originally accessioned in June, 2000 and filed under Acc. #855.; Large bolt-bound ledger book. Fabric covers with red leather corners. Good condition, however item gives off redrot residue from corners. Ledger is heavy, handle with care. (Carton 3, Binder 1)
  - General Ledger, 1950 - 1980; Ledger including sections on cash, accounts receivable, prepaid expense - hospital, student loans (cash/investments, loans receivable), 1963 bonds cash investments, real estate control, equipment, miscellaneous, deferred income and deposits, restricted funds, surplus net investment, student loan funds, 1963 bond surplus accrued interest pay, notes and bonds - payable, tuition fees, miscellaneous fees, investment income, gifts, research grants, miscellaneous income, student activities, medical center income, student aid, residence halls, expense control, medical center expense, capital expenditures, sorority halls, auxiliary expenditures, and miscellaneous assets. Ledger is infrequently updated between the 1950s and 1980s. (Carton 4, Binder 1)
  - Real Estate Ledger (GWU), 1880 - 1980; Black bolt bound binder (1920s era from Stationers Loose Leaf Company). Very Good Condition. Heavy, handle with care. (Carton 5, Binder 1)
  - General Funds - Loan Funds, 1960s - 1970s; Ledger pages of scholarship funds from between the 1960s and 1970s. Updated to include information on gifts, awards, and interest, among other things. Organized as originally cataloged by the Office of the Comptroller. Originally part of Acc. #855 as Item 3, "Loan Fund/Restricted Fund Ledger c. 1962- c. 1976". Rehoused from ledger binder into folders in November, 2019. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - General Ledger - Restricted Funds (A-L), 1960s - 1970s; Ledger pages of general fund restricited funds from between the 1960s and 1970s. Updated to include information on gifts, awards, and interest, among other things. Organized alphabetically by name of scholarship as originally cataloged by the Office of the Comptroller. Originally part of Acc. #855 as Item 3, "Loan Fund/Restricted Fund Ledger c. 1962- c. 1976". Rehoused from ledger binder into folders in November, 2019. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - General Ledger - Restricted Funds (M-Z), 1960s - 1970s; Ledger pages of general fund restricited funds from between the 1960s and 1970s. Updated to include information on gifts, awards, and interest, among other things. Organized alphabetically by name of scholarship as originally cataloged by the Office of the Comptroller. Originally part of Acc. #855 as Item 3, "Loan Fund/Restricted Fund Ledger c. 1962- c. 1976". Rehoused from ledger binder into folders in November, 2019. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Restrictive Income - Account 1100, 1957 - 1970; Rehoused from a binder titled "Restrictive Income - Sep. 1, 1946 - June 30, 1969." Originally listed in Acc. 855 - Item 4. Includes infromation about accounts all labeled under Account 1100. Updates on these accounts range from between 1957 - 1970. (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Restrictive Income - Accounts 10 - 80, 1946 - 1972; Rehoused from a binder titled "Restrictive Income - Sep. 1, 1946 - June 30, 1969." Originally listed in Acc. 855 - Item 4. Records ordered alphabetically, reflecting how they were originally ordered. Includes information about accounts all labeled under Accounts 10-80. Updates on these accounts range from between 1946 - 1972. (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Restrictive Income - Accounts 10-80, 1946 - 1972; Rehoused from a binder titled "Restrictive Income - Sep. 1, 1946 - June 30, 1969." Originally listed in Acc. 855 - Item 4. Records ordered alphabetically, reflecting how they were originally ordered. Includes information about accounts all labeled under Accounts 10-80. Updates on these accounts range from between 1946 - 1972. (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Restrictive Income - Account 1300 (A), 1946 - 1970; Rehoused from a binder titled "Restrictive Income - Sep. 1, 1946 - June 30, 1969." Originally listed in Acc. 855 - Item 4. Records ordered alphabetically, reflecting how they were originally ordered. Includes information about accounts all labeled under Accounts 10-80. Updates on these accounts range from between 1946 - 1970. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Restrictive Income - Account 1300 (B), 1946 - 1970; Rehoused from a binder titled "Restrictive Income - Sep. 1, 1946 - June 30, 1969." Originally listed in Acc. 855 - Item 4. Records ordered alphabetically, reflecting how they were originally ordered. Includes information about accounts all labeled under Accounts 1300, starting with the letter B. Updates on these accounts range from between 1946 - 1970. (Box 7, Folder 4)